Guide to the Strong Museum Collection ARS.0190
Archive of Recorded Sound
Strong Museum Collection
1825-1926
Archive of Recorded Sound
Aeolian Company
Mason & Hamlin
Amphion Piano Player Company
Strong (History Museum)
ARS.0190
22 box(es) 22 records storage boxes (22 linear feet), including 129 bound volumes and 1 folder
The Strong Museum Collection contains piano, organ, player piano, and player organ patents in bound volumes from the Aeolian, Amphion, and Mason & Hamlin companies. These date from circa 1825 to 1926 and are organized by dates and alphabetical indexes. Also included is 1 envelope entitled 'Aeolian American Action'; undated.
Scope and Contents
The Strong Museum Collections consists of piano, player piano, organ, and player organ patents in 129 bound volumes from the Aeolian, Amphion, and Mason & Hamlin companies. The majority of the patent volumes are from the United States Patent Office but there are a small number from the English Patent Office. The volumes date from circa 1825 to 1926, and are organized first by company, instrument and chronologically. There are also alphabetical indexes. Also included is one envelope entitled ‘Aeolian American Action’; undated, which contains an advertisement. The collection is in original order and each bound volume retains the Strong Museum call numbers in square brackets at the end of the volume title.
Biographical / Historical
The Aeolian company, founded in 1887 by William Tremaine, was a manufacturer of player organs and pianos. Mason & Hamlin, based in Haverhill, Massachusetts, is a piano manufacturer that was founded in 1854 by Henry Mason and Emmons Hamlin. The Strong is an educational museum in Rochester, New York. The museum’s name has slowly evolved from the Margaret Woodbury Strong Museum to the Strong Museum to the Strong National Museum of Play and finally The Strong.
(Source: Wikipedia, 2017-12-21)
Arrangement
This collection is in original order and arranged into five series: Series 1: Aeolian Company, 1839-1926 Series 2: The Amphion Company, 1901-1926 Series 3: Mason & Hamlin Company, 1825-1909 Series 4: Patents Index, 1849-1913 Series 5: Patents of Player Action, etc., 1900-1908
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive of Recorded Sound for assistance. Some of the bound volumes are fragile and may require special care during handling.
Mechanical musical instruments; Mechanical organ builders; Mechanical organs; Musical instrument makers; musical instruments and equipment; Musical inventions and patents; Organ builders; Organ (Musical instrument); Patents--Great Britain; Patents--United States; Piano; Player piano; Player organ; Aeolian Company; Mason & Hamlin; Amphion Piano Player Company; Strong (History Museum)
- Series 1: Aeolian Company, 1839-1926
  Arrangement
  This series is in original order and organized into four sub-series: Aeolian Company Patents, 1867-1924 British Patents, Music and Musical Instruments, 1877-1902 Mechanical Musical Instruments, 1849-1924 Piano Patents, 1839-1926
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains piano, organ, player piano, and player organ patents in 62 bound volumes from the Aeolian company. The majority of the patent volumes are from the United States Patent Office but there are a small number from the English Patent Office. The volumes date from circa 1839 to 1926, and are organized by dates and alphabetical indexes. Also included is one envelope entitled ‘Aeolian American Action’; undated, which contains an advertisement.
  - Sub-series I: Aeolian Company Patents, 1867-1924
    This sub-series contains patents from the Aeolian company in 4 bound volumes. All of the patent volumes are from the United States Patent Office. The volumes dates from 1867 to 1924, and are organized chronologically.
    - Aeolian Company Patents, Volume 1 [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.619], 1867-1888 (Box 1, Volume 1)
    - Aeolian Company Patents, Volume 2 [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.620], 1888-1904 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    - Aeolian Company Patents, Volume 3 [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.621], 1904-1913 (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - Aeolian Company Patents, Volume 4 [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.622], 1913-1924 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Sub-series II: British Patents, Music and Musical Instruments, 1877-1902
    This sub-series contains piano, organ, player piano, and player organ patents in 8 bound volumes from the Aeolian company. All of the patent volumes are from the English Patent Office. The volumes dates from 1877 to 1902, and are organized chronologically.
    - British Patents, Music and Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.623], 1877-1884 (Box 1, Volume 5)
    - British Patents, Music and Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.624], 1888-1890 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    - British Patents, Music and Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.625], 1891-1893 (Box 2, Volume 2)
    - British Patents, Music and Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.626], 1894-1896 (Box 2, Volume 3)
    - British Patents, Music and Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.627], 1897-1898 (Box 2, Volume 4)
    - British Patents, Music and Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.628], 1899 (Box 2, Volume 5)
    - British Patents, Music and Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.629], 1900-1901 (Box 2, Volume 6)
    - British Patents, Music and Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.630], 1902 (Box 2, Volume 7)
  - Sub-series III: Mechanical Musical Instruments, 1849-1924
    This sub-series contains mechanical musical instrument patents in 35 bound volumes. All of the patent volumes are from the United States Patent Office. The volumes date from 1849 to 1924, and are organized chronologically. Also included is one envelope entitled ‘Aeolian American Action’; undated, which contains an advertisement.
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.631], 1849-1888 (Box 2, Volume 8)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.632], 1881-1885 (Box 3, Volume 1)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.633], 1886-1888 (Box 3, Volume 2)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.634], 1889-1907 (Box 3, Volume 3)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.635], 1896-1898 (Box 3, Volume 4)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.636], 1899-1900 (Box 3, Volume 5)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.637], 1901 (Box 3, Volume 6)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.638], 1902 (Box 4, Volume 1)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.639], 1903 (Box 4, Volume 2)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.640], 1904 (Box 4, Volume 3)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.641], 1905 (Box 4, Volume 4)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.642], 1906 (Box 4, Volume 5)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.643], 1907 (Box 5, Volume 1)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.644], 1908 (Box 5, Volume 2)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.645], 1909 (Box 5, Volume 3)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.646], 1910 (Box 5, Volume 4)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.647], 1911 (Box 5, Volume 5)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.648], 1912 (Box 6, Volume 1)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.649], 1912 (Box 6, Volume 2)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.650], 1913 (Box 6, Volume 3)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.651], 1913 (Box 6, Volume 4)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.652], 1914 (Box 6, Volume 5)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.653], 1914 (Box 6, Volume 6)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.654], 1915 (Box 7, Volume 1)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.655], 1915 (Box 7, Volume 2)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.656], 1916 (Box 7, Volume 3)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.657], 1916 (Box 7, Volume 4)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.658], 1916 (Box 7, Volume 5)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.659], 1918 (Box 7, Volume 6)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.660], 1918 (Box 8, Volume 1)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.661], 1919 (Box 8, Volume 2)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.662], 1920 (Box 8, Volume 3)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.663], 1921 (Box 8, Volume 4)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.664], 1922 (Box 8, Volume 5)
    - Mechanical Musical Instruments [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.665], 1923-1924 (Box 8, Volume 6)
    - Aeolian American Action advertisement, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Sub-series VI: Piano Patents, 1839-1926
    This sub-series contains piano patents in 15 bound volumes. All of the patent volumes are from the United States Patent Office. The volumes date from 1839 to 1926, and are organized chronologically.
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.666], 1839-1870 (Box 9, Volume 1)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.667], 1871-1877 (Box 9, Volume 2)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.668], 1878-1882 (Box 9, Volume 3)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.669], 1883-1886 (Box 9, Volume 4)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.670], 1887-1889 (Box 9, Volume 5)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.671], 1890-1891 (Box 9, Volume 6)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.672], 1892-1894 (Box 10, Volume 1)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.673], 1895-1897 (Box 10, Volume 2)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.674], 1898-1900 (Box 10, Volume 3)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.675], 1901-1903 (Box 10, Volume 4)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.676], 1904-1905 (Box 10, Volume 5)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.677], 1906-1908 (Box 10, Volume 6)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.678], 1909-1912 (Box 11, Volume 1)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.679], 1917-1921 (Box 11, Volume 2)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.680], 1922-1926 (Box 11, Volume 3)
- Series 2: The Amphion Company, 1901-1926
  This series is in original order and is organized in two series: Index to Patents, undated Piano Player Patents, 1901-1926
  This series contains piano, organ, player piano, and player organ patents in 34 bound volumes from the Amphion Company. The majority of the volumes are either patent indexes or piano player patents. The volumes date from circa 1901 to 1926, and are organized alphabetically.
  - Sub-series I: Index to Patents, 1860-1904
    This sub-series contains indexes for piano, organ, player piano, and player organ patents in 12 bound volumes from the Amphion Company. The volumes date from 1860-1904 and are organized alphabetically by patent holder
    - Index to Patents A, B [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.681], 1864-1904 (Box 11, Volume 4)
    - Index to Patents C [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.682], 1867-1904 (Box 11, Volume 5)
    - Index to Patents D, E, F [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.683], 1860-1904 (Box 11, Volume 6)
    - Index to Patents G [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.684], 1871-1904 (Box 12, Volume 1)
    - Index to Patents H [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.685], 1877-1904 (Box 12, Volume 2)
    - Index to Patents I, J, K, L [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.686], 1879-1904 (Box 12, Volume 3)
    - Index to Patents M, N, O [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.687], 1870-1904 (Box 12, Volume 4)
    - Index to Patents P [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.688], 1863-1904 (Box 12, Volume 5)
    - Index to Patents S [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.689], 1866-1904 (Box 12, Volume 6)
    - Index to Patents T, U, V [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.690], 1866-1904 (Box 12, Volume 7)
    - Index to Patents W [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.691], 1866-1904 (Box 12, Volume 8)
    - Index to Patents R, Y, Z [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.692], 1869-1904 (Box 13, Volume 1)
  - Sub-series II: Piano Player Patents, 1901-1926
    This sub-series contains player piano patents in 22 bound volumes from the Amphion Company. The volumes date from 1901 to 1926, and are organized alphabetically.
    - Piano Player Patents A-B [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.693], 1903-1912 (Box 13, Volume 2)
    - Piano Player Patents C-D [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.694], 1903-1912 (Box 13, Volume 3)
    - Piano Player Patents E-H [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.695], 1903-1912 (Box 13, Volume 4)
    - Piano Player Patents J-P [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.696], 1903-1912 (Box 13, Volume 5)
    - Piano Player Patents R-V [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.697], 1903-1912 (Box 13, Volume 6)
    - Piano Player Patents W-Z [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.698], 1903-1912 (Box 13, Volume 7)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.699], 1901-1903 (Box 14, Volume 1)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.700], 1904-1906 (Box 14, Volume 2)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.701], 1907 (Box 14, Volume 3)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.702], 1912 (Box 14, Volume 4)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.703], 1912 (Box 14, Volume 5)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.704], 1914 (Box 15, Volume 1)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.705], 1915 (Box 15, Volume 2)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.706], 1916 (Box 15, Volume 3)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.707], 1917 (Box 15, Volume 4)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.708], 1918 (Box 16, Volume 1)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.709], 1919 (Box 16, Volume 2)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.710], 1920 (Box 16, Volume 3)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.711], 1921 (Box 16, Volume 4)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.712], 1922 (Box 16, Volume 5)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.713], 1923 (Box 16, Volume 6)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.714], 1924 (Box 17, Volume 1)
    - Piano Player Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.715], 1926 (Box 17, Volume 2)
- Series 3: Mason & Hamlin Company, 1825-1909
  This series is in original order and is organized in two series: Organ Patents, 1838-1908 Piano Patents, 1825-1909
  This series contains organ and piano patents in 27 bound volumes from the Mason & Hamlin company. The volumes date from 1825 to 1909, and are organized by instrument and then chronologically.
  - Sub-series I: Organ Patents, 1838-1908
    This sub-series contains organ patents in 12 bound volumes from the Mason & Hamlin company. The volumes date from circa 1838 to 1908, and are organized chronologically.
    - Organ Patents, Index organ [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.716], 1838-1908 (Box 17, Volume 3)
    - Organ Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.717], 1838-1868 (Box 17, Volume 4)
    - Organ Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.718], 1869-1872 (Box 17, Volume 5)
    - Organ Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.719], 1873-1875 (Box 17, Volume 6)
    - Organ Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.720], 1876-1879 (Box 17, Volume 7)
    - Organ Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.721], 1880-1883 (Box 18, Volume 1)
    - Organ Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.722], 1884-1888 (Box 18, Volume 2)
    - Organ Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.723], 1889-1892 (Box 18, Volume 3)
    - Organ Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.724], 1893-1894 (Box 18, Volume 4)
    - Organ Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.725], 1895-1897 (Box 18, Volume 5)
    - Organ Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.726], 1901-1903 (Box 18, Volume 6)
    - Organ Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.727], 1907-1908 (Box 18, Volume 7)
  - Sub-series II: Piano Patents, 1825-1909
    This sub-series contains piano patents in 15 bound volumes from the Mason & Hamlin company. The volumes date from 1825 to 1909, and are organized chronologically.
    - Piano Patents, Index piano [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.728], 1825-1909 (Box 19, Volume 1)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.729], 1825-1867 (Box 19, Volume 2)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.730], 1868-1871 (Box 19, Volume 3)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.731], 1872-1875 (Box 19, Volume 4)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.732], 1876-1878 (Box 19, Volume 5)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.733], 1879-1883 (Box 19, Volume 6)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.734], 1884-1886 (Box 19, Volume 7)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.735], 1887-1889 (Box 20, Volume 1)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.736], 1890-1891 (Box 20, Volume 2)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.737], 1892-1893 (Box 20, Volume 3)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.738], 1894 (Box 20, Volume 4)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.739], 1896-1898 (Box 20, Volume 5)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.740], 1898-1900 (Box 20, Volume 6)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.741], 1907-1908 (Box 21, Volume 1)
    - Piano Patents [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.742], 1909 (Box 21, Volume 2)
- Series 4: Patents Index, 1849-1913
  This series is in original order.
  This series contains piano, organ, player piano, and player organ patents indexes in 3 bound volumes. The volumes date from 1849 to 1913, and are organized alphabetically by patent holder.
  - Patent Index A-M [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.743], 1849-1913 (Box 21, Volume 3)
  - Patent Index N-Z [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.744], 1849-1913 (Box 21, Volume 4)
  - Patent Index (Chronological by patent #) [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.745], 1849-1913 (Box 22, Volume 1)
- Series 5: Patents of Player Action, Etc., 1900-1908
  This series contains piano player patents in 3 bound volumes. The volumes date from 1900 to 1908, and are arranged chronologically.
  - Patents of Player Action, Etc. [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.746 Vol. 1], 1900-1904 (Box 22, Volume 2)
  - Patents of Player Action, Etc. [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.747 Vol. 2], 1905-1907 (Box 22, Volume 3)
  - Patents of Player Action, Etc. [Strong Museum call number 87.3000.748 Vol. 3], 1908 (Box 22, Volume 4)